Guide to the Leo Hershokowitz Collection of Newspaper Illustrations and Billheads 1840's-1911 PR 263
New-York Historical Society
Leo Hershkowitz Collection of Newspaper Illustrations and Billheads
1840's - 1911
New-York Historical Society
PR 263
8.04 Linear feet (6 boxes)
This collection includes tear sheets from 19th-century American and foreign illustrated newspapers, arranged by subject. Also includes a smaller number of illustrated trade bills.
Provenance
Multiple gifts from Leo Hershkowitz and his son, Herbert Berger-Hershkowitz, 2007, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
This collection of illustrated newspapers and billheads was compiled by historian Leo Hershkowitz, long-time professor at Queens College who retired in 2005.
Newspaper illustrations with wood engravings became very popular around the mid-nienteenth century. It was at this time that a number of developments made it practical to produce a newspaper filled with illustrations. First, wood engraving was a relief process, so the images could be printed from the same presses, and even on the same page as typeface. Secondly, procedures were developed which made it quick and easy to go from a manuscript drawing to a print, and then steel facing allowed for the production of thousands of images from the engraved woodblocks.
The first newspaper to feature wood-cut illustrations was The Illustrated London News, founded in 1842. In 1851, the first American illustrated newspaper appeared. Originally called Gleason's Pictorial Drawing-Room Companion, its name was changed to Ballou's Pictorial Drawing-Room Companion in 1855. Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper appeared in 1855, followed two years later by the most successful of all the American illustrated newspapers, Harper's Weekly. Many other illustrated newspapers appeared in different countries and an article in The Graphic (London), December 6, 1890, depicted the mast heads of twenty-three illustrated newspapers from around the world.
The success of these newspapers lay in their illustrations. These images were wide-ranging in their coverage of events, places, things and persons of interest to the readers, and they were extremely timely in their appearance, often being issued within two weeks of when the images were first drawn. Readers found it new and exciting to be able to have, within days and at an affordable price, a first-hand view of a disaster from across the country, to gaze on an image of a just constructed bridge, or to see contemporary pictures of far-away cities or countries. The prints produced in the nineteenth-century illustrated newspapers were comprehensive in subject and ubiquitous, with the most successful weeklies having press runs of well over 100,000 for each issue. The quality of the engraving is generally very good and many of the drawings were by skilled artists.
In addition to their artistic quality, newspaper illustrations often provide the most accurate and current images done of their subjects, and in some cases these are the only contemporary images of the people, buildings, and events depicted. There were often separately issued prints of the most famous individuals, the most spectacular disasters, the most substantial new structures, the most significant political events, and the most populous cities, but there were thousands of people, events, structures, towns and cities for which illustrated newspaper prints were the only contemporary images ever done.
Illustrated billheads date back to the early 19th century and typically pictured the seller's place of business.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of tear sheets from American and foreign illustrated newspapers, arranged by subject. Newspapers represented include Harper's Weekly, Frank Leslie's, Gleason's Pictorial Drawing Room Companion, Illustrated London News, Illustrated News of the World, and others.
A smaller number of illustrated trade bills from New York City businesses are also included.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
- Series I: Newspaper Illustrations -- Civil War Era
  Scope and Contents
  This series spans the period from 1853-1911 and contains illustrations depicting the American Civil War from both Harper's Weekly and Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspapers.
  - Subseries I.1: Single Sheet Illustrations
    This subseries is comprised of individual newspaper pages. The illustrations are arranged by subject, then by date. These single page tear sheets may have either one large illustration or several smaller illustrations, often showing more than one subject. When a page contains more than one subject, the most prominent image is used for arrangement.
    Harper's Ferry Raid contains illustrations regarding the raid, the arrest of John Brown and his soldiers, as well as their execution.
    Battle Views contains pictorial illustrations depicting various skirmishes, battles and campaigns throughout the Civil War. These images all show soldiers in action.
    Naval Views contains illustrations of naval ships and battles, as well as images of harbors and of soldiers traveling by ship or boat.
    Military Life includes illustrations of soldiers in non-combat situations. These include soldiers marching, voting, and recovering from battle, views of camp life and depictions of the daily lives of these men. These folders also contain images of military prisons, prison camps, and captured soldiers, as well as hospitals and wounded soldiers and their injuries.
    Civilian Life is comprised of a variety of depictions of life outside the military during the civil war. These images show everything from starving refugees to winter recreation. There are also illustrations of crimes, criminals and trials, unrelated to the war. Illustrations regarding the Harper's Ferry Raid, John Brown's arrest & execution can also be found here.
    U.S. Government contains images of politicians and political meetings.
    Geographic View includes maps, birds-eye views and general views of the United States as well as other countries. This group also includes several images of statues and monuments.
    Portraits contains drawn portraits of both military men and civilians. Included are "Missing Men" illustrations, portraits with a brief description of the persons last whereabouts, posted in the classified section of the newspapers.
    Cartoons & Caricatures includes commentary on everything from the war to women's fashion. The majority of these cartoons were printed among classified ads, which also reflect the needs and interests of society, even in wartime.
    Post Civil War Images is comprised of illustrations from newspapers published well after the Civil War's end. Several of these images are heroic depictions of the war. This group also contains images of Civil War veterans, with one image showing veterans reunited at the fiftieth anniversary of the Battle of Bull Run.
    - Harpers Ferry Raid, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Battle Scenes, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Battle Scenes, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Battle Scenes, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Battle Scenes, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Battle Scenes, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Naval Views, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Naval Views, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Naval Views, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Naval Views, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Military Life, 1858, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Military Life, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Military Life, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Military Life, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Military Life, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Military Life, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Military Life - Hospitals, 1861-1865 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Military Life - Prisons/Prisoners, 1861-1865 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Civilian Life, 1860-1861 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Civilian Life, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Civilian Life, 1863-1864 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Civilian Life, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Civilian Life - Crimes and Criminals, 1853-1865, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - U.S. Government, 1853-1860 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Views - Miscellaneous, 1858-1865 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Views - Georgia, 1860-1865 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Views - SOuth Carolina, 1860-1865 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Views - Virginia, 1859-1865 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Monumnets and Statues, 1860-1890 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Views - Foreign, 1863-1865 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Portraits - Miscellaneous Military, 1858-1865 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Portraits - Generals, A-Z, 1861-1865, 1891, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Portraits - Miscellaneous Sailors, 1860-1865, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Portraits - Miscellaneous, A-Z, 1853-1865, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Group Portraits - Miscellaneous, A-Z, 1860-1865 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Portraits - Missing Men, 1860-1862 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Cartoons/Caricatures, 1860-1861 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Cartoons/Caricatures, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Cartoons/Caricatures, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Cartoons/Caricatures, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Cartoons/Caricatures, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Post-Civil War Images, 1868-1911 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Subseries I.2: Double Sheet Ilustrations
    This subseries is comprised of illustrations spanning two full newspaper pages. The illustrations are arranged by subject, then by date. Because of their size, they are housed separately from the single sheets, in flat file drawers.
    Significant illustrations in this series include a graphic depiction of Andersonville Prison (in Military Life), an allegorical image entitled Uprising of the North (in Battle Scenes), and a portrayal of the House of Representatives following the passage of the thirteenth amendment, abolishing slavery (in Civilian Life).
    - Battle Scenes, 1862-1865 (Oversize Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - Naval scenes, 1862-1863, 1865 (Oversize Flat files, Folder FF2)
    - Military Life, 1861-1865, 1910 (Oversize Flat files, Folder FF3)
    - Civilian Life, 1860, 1862, 1865 (Oversize Flat files, Folder FF4)
    - Geographic Views, 1862 (Oversize Flat files, Folder FF5)
- Series II: Newspaper Illustrations -- Assorted Subjects
  This series includes tear sheets from American and British illustrated newspapers, arranged by subject. Images show aspects of daily life, important news and cultural events, and fanciful illustrations on a wide variety of topics.
  - Disasters: Fires and Floods, 1843-1902 (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
  - Disasters: Mississippi Flood, 1858-1860, 1882-1890 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Religion, 1840's-1850's (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Religion, 1860's (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Religion, 1870's (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Religion, 1880's (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Religion, 1890's (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Ships, 1856-1889 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Foreign Views, 1850's-1890's (Box 5, Folder 52-56)
  - Travel and Transportation, 1850's-1890's (Box 5, Folder 57)
- Series III: Billheads
  This series contains 19th century illustrated trade bills from New York City businesses. These trade bills were apparently exhibited at some point, and are housed with exhibition labels and color snapshots, circa 2000, of the locations depicted on the trade bills. Also included is one folder of New York City bonds.
  - American Hotel, 1833, 1851 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Astor House, 1849 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Baker & Godwin, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Carlton House, 1842 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Cushing, Bardua & Co., 1878 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Delameter Iron Works, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - DDevlin & Co., 1875 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Fairbanks & Co., 1872 (Box 6, Folder unknown container)
  - Fifth Avenue Hotel, 1860 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - John Florence, Jr. [Hotel], 1847 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Garret & Green, 1848 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - E.V. Haughwout & Co., 1857 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Jacob Hay Jr., 1864 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Thomas Hope & Co., 1856 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Irving House, 1849 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - David Jones Brewery, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Lovejoy's Hotel, 1858 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Marvin Safe Co., 1874 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Morgan Iron Works, 1870 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - New York Hotel [to Henry Clay Committee], 1848 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Pear Street House, 1842 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - St. Nicholas Hotel, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Henry Seibert Brothers, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - H. Sperry & Co., 1857 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Steinway & Sons, 1876 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Grant Thorburn & Son, 1832 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - William M. Tweed [Chairs], 1857 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - B. M. Westbrook, 1868 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - City of New York Stocks and Bonds, 1869-1871 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Assorted billheads, 1859-1884 (Box 6, Folder 30)